千百年来我们一直在仰望夜空
For thousands of years, we have looked at the night sky...
认为发光体
and believed that the illuminated stuff...
就是构成我们宇宙的一切
was all that made up our universe.
科学家现在认识到了并非闪闪发光的
Scientists now realize it's not what shines in the light...
而是隐藏在暗处的东西
but what hides in the dark...
掌握着我们天空真正的秘密
that holds the true secrets of our sky.
有一个神秘的暗物质
There is a mysterious dark matter...
将恒星与星系结合在一起
that binds stars and galaxies together...
弱相互作用重粒子[WIMPS]
and strange particles like WlMPS,
轴子[axions]及大质量天体物理密实晕体[MACHOs]之类的奇异粒子
axions, and MACHOs...
可能是始作俑者
might be to blame.
有一种黑暗的排斥能量
And there is a dark, repulsive energy...
正在创造宇宙的空间
that is creating space in the universe...
但又在将星系逐步逐步地拆散
but driving the galaxies further and further apart...
直至悲惨的结局
to a dismal fate.
暗物质和暗能量结合在一起
Combined, dark matter and dark energy...
占到了宇宙的96%
make up ninety-six percent of the universe...
揭开它们的秘密
and uncovering their secrets...
就像是百步穿杨
is like making the one-in-a-million shot.
一旦揭开 宇宙的最终结局
lf uncovered, the ultimate fate of the universe...
就有可能被揭示
might be revealed.
它会是在引力的猛烈撞击中垮塌燃烧
Will it crash and burn in a horrific collision...of gravitational forces...
还是暗能量将宇宙撕得粉碎呢？
or will dark energy tear the universe apart?
打赌 宇宙将葬身冰寒
The betting is the universe will die in ice.
了解这两个量… 暗物质和暗能量
Understanding these two quantities, dark matter and dark energy...
其实是了解宇宙的根本
is really fundamental to understanding the universe.
这是一次宇宙黑暗一面的旅行
This is a trip to the dark side of the universe.
这是搜寻暗物质和暗能量之旅
This is the hunt for "Dark Matter and Dark Energy."
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制:春树  字幕来源:五羊皮  调校:御雪寒狼  招募Q号:76846146
[历史频道] 第二季 第六集 暗物质和暗能量
[History Channel] The UniverseⅡ 06of19 Dark.Matter&Dark.Energy
暗物质完全不同于我们在地球上所遇到的任何东西
Dark matter is unlike anything we have ever encountered on Earth.
每一秒钟有数十亿个奇异粒子
Billions of these strange particles...
穿过它们所遇到的任何东西
pass through everything they encounter each second.
它们具有巨大的影响力
They are so massive in weight...
具有影响星系的能力
they have the power to influence the galaxies...
它们的形成和它们旋转的速度
how they form and howfast they spin.
暗物质的无形之手无处不在
Dark matter"s invisible presence is everywhere...
或许是这样的
or so it seems.
科学没有直接证明暗物质粒子的存在
Science has not directly proven dark matter particles exist.
有许多怀疑但没有答案
There are many suspects, but no answers...
观察你无法看到的东西谈何容易
and observing something you can't see isn't easy.
它并不发光也并不吸收光
lt doesn't emit light, and it doesn't absorb light.
它对光根本就无动于衷
lt doesn't interact with light at all.
它不仅不发光
Not only does it not shine...
而且你还无法隐约看到它
you can't easily see it in obscuration.
然而科学知道其证据的存在
But the evidence is there. Science knows it.
地球上的每一本教科书
Every textbook on the planet Earth...
都说宇宙是原子和某些亚原子构成的
says that the universe is made out of atoms...and some subatomic particles.
啊!所有这些教科书都是错误的
Well, all those textbooks are wrong.
他们将去地底下给予证明
And they are going underground to prove it.
当他们听说这个不可见的物质叫做暗物质时
When they hear about this invisible matter...
他们说:"呸 胡说"
called dark matter, they say, "Bah, humbug."
拿出暗物质存在的证据
"Show me proof that dark matter exists."
明尼苏达州… 苏丹 远离大城市灯光200英里
Soudan, Minnesota, 200 miles from any major city lights...
一个搜寻暗物质的理想之地
a perfect place for hunting dark matter...
但是并非为了显而易见的原因
but not for obvious reasons.
那么你会认为我们想仰望星空来寻找暗物质
So you'd think we'd want to look up in the sky for dark matter.
那里毕竟是暗物质来的地方
That's where dark matter is coming from, after all.
恰恰相反我们将带上头盔
But instead, we're going to don our helmets...
深入到这个矿井的下面
and we're going to walk down into this mine.
地下2431英尺的地方是苏丹国家实验室
2,431 feet underground is the Soudan National Laboratory...
一个废弃的铁矿改造成了一个研究机构
an abandoned iron mine reconfigured into a research facility.
这里只是全球许多实验室之一
This is just one lab of many around the world...
放在地下是为了让实验免遭宇宙射线
going underground to shield experiments from cosmic rays.
每一个都在争相发现暗物质
Each are racing to detect dark matter...
一种只能间接观察的无形粒子
an invisible particle that has only been indirectly observed...
但从未捕获过
but never captured.
我们在这里已经有10年了
We've been at this for, now, a decade...
尚未看到过一个暗物质粒子
and we have yet to see a dark matter particle.
搜寻暗物质始于近一个世纪前
The hunt for dark matter started almost a century ago.
天文学家终于有了深入夜空观察的工具
Astronomers finally had the tools to see deep into the night sky...
问题出现了
and the questions began.
直至1920年代后
So it wasn't until the 1920s...
科技有了长足的发展
that the technology developed well enough...
以致我们能够对这些模糊的小斑点
so that we could take the little fuzzy patches...
人们已经在望远镜里注意到了
that people had noticed in their telescopes...
进行分析并搞清楚它们是什么东西
and resolve them and figure out what they are.
当时埃德温·哈勃震惊了世界
Then, Edwin Hubble shocked the world...
宣称宇宙远不止银河系
and declared the universe was bigger thanjust the Milky Way.
人们意识到这些模糊的小斑点中的某些
People realized that some of these little fuzzy patches...
是单个的星系 就像我们的银河系一样
are separate galaxies, just like our Milky Way galaxy.
在天文学家发现新的星系的同时
As astronomers discovered new galaxies...
加州理工学院教授弗里茨·兹维基仰望
Cal Tech professor Fritz Zwicky looked up...
后发星系团周边
to the neighboring Coma Cluster of galaxies...
观察到了一些奇怪的东西
and observed something strange.
在他测量后发星系团运动的时候
When he measured what the motions were...in the Coma Cluster of galaxies...
他得出了那个星团有多少质量的估计值
he got an estimate for how much mass there was in that cluster.
在他比较有多少质量时
Then he compared it to how much mass...
你其实可以通过观察那些星系来看到
you could actually see by looking at the galaxies.
有些东西并未增加
Something didn't add up.
星系在星团里运动迅速
The galaxies were moving too fast within the cluster...
相对他能看到的发光物质的数量
for the amount of illuminated stuff he could see.
通过他的计算
By his calculations...
那里应该有发光物质160多倍的物质
there should have been 160 times more illuminated mass...
来解释星团里的星系的随机速度
to account for the random speeds of galaxies in the cluster.
有别的什么东西在影响着它们的运动
Something else was affecting their motions...
然而是什么东东呢？
but what was it?
他分析了它们的运动
He analyzed their motions...
断定那个星团并不稳定
and concluded that the cluster could not be stable...
除非有大量的暗物质存在
unless there was a large amount of dark matter present.
1933年他是最早真正领悟
ln 1933, he was one of the first people...
暗物质存在意义的人之一
to really grasp the significance...of the presence of dark matter.
他称它为… 失踪的物质
He called it "missing matter."
暗物质:一种无形的物质 具有万有引力的吸引力
Dark matter, an invisible mass that was gravitationally attractive...
能够影响到星团里全部星系的速度
and was able to affect the speeds...of entire galaxies in a cluster.
革命性的思想？
Revolutionary thinking?
对 但是这一发现很大程度被忽视了
Yes, but the discovery was largely ignored.
我认为人们把兹维基当真
l think that people took Zwicky seriously...
但是他们不敢妄下结论
but they didn'tjump to any conclusions.
那时宇宙才刚刚开始探索
This was a time when the universe...was just beginning to be explored.
到了1920年我们才认识到
lt was the 1920s when we first realized...
我们的星系以外还有星系
there were galaxies outside our own.
我们过去不知道它就是星系还是
What we didn't know back then was whether it was simply galaxies...
恒星 气体 尘埃 我们无法看到
or stars or gas or dust that we couldn't see...
它是不是什么完全不同的东西
or whether it was something truly different.
兹维基的意见基于测量恒星和星系的质量
Zwicky's observations were based on measuring the mass...in the stars and galaxies.
然而你是如何称重空间的东西的呢？
But how do you weigh stuff in space?
你不可能将太阳放在天平上的
You can't go and put the Sun on a scale.
这有那么一点困难
lt's a little bit hard.
然而你能做的就是你可以测量
But what you can do is you can measure...
行星围绕着太阳运转的速度
how fast the planets are moving around the Sun.
太阳里的物质越多
And the more stuff there is in the Sun...
这些行星必定会在自己的轨道上运转得越快
the faster those planets have to move...to stay in their orbits.
牛顿和爱因斯坦都说过
Newton and Einstein both said...
一个物体中的质量或东西越多
the more mass or stuff you have in an object...
其所具有的万有引力就越强
the more gravitational pull it will have.
物体距离其中心越远
And the further an object is from the center...
在轨运行就应该越慢
the slower it should travel in orbit...
这是因为万有引力较弱的缘故
because the gravitational pull is weaker.
根据爱因斯坦的广义相对论
According to Einstein's general theory of relativity...
乃至根据牛顿的万有引力理论
or even according to Newtonian gravity...
所有这些星系都相互吸引着
all of the galaxies are pulling on each other.
就像太阳影响着我们的太阳系
lt's like the Sun's influence on our solar system.
太阳的质量拽拉水星要快于冥王星
The mass of the Sun pulls Mercury faster than Pluto...
因为水星的位置更靠近太阳
because Mercury is positioned closer to the Sun.
同样对于一个星系来说你可以预料到
Likewise for a galaxy, you would expect...
随着你越来越远
as you got further and further away...
物体在其轨道上的的运动也就越来越慢
things are moving more and more slowly...to stay in their orbits.
然而兹维基并未观察到这个情况
But Zwicky didn't observe that.
同样50年后的一个年轻科学家维拉·鲁宾也为观察到
Neither did a young scientist named Vera Rubin fifty years later.
她在观察类似银河系这样的星系的旋转曲线
She was observing the rotational curves...of galaxies similar to the Milky Way.
和兹维基一样她的意见同样看似怪异
Like Zwicky, her observations also seemed strange.
维拉·鲁宾实际测量到的是
What Vera Rubin actually measured was...
随着你越来越远
as you got further and further away...
旋转的气体和尘埃的速度始终如一
the velocity of the orbiting gas and dust remained constant.
鲁宾观察到的就好象城市比作星系
What Rubin observed was as if a citywere a galaxy...
路上的每一辆汽车就是行星或恒星
and every car on the road was a planet or star.
不管交通流量如何
And despite the amount of traffic...
整个城市里的每辆汽车的速度都是相同的
every car traveled around the city at the same speed.
这种同样恒定的运转速度
This same, consistent rotational speed...
不管物质的量 交通量如何
despite the amount of stuff, or traffic...
这就是鲁宾世纪观察到的情况
was exactly what Rubin observed.
星系的外围部分运转得够快
The outer parts of the galaxy were rotating fast enough...
必定会有更多的物质
that there must be a lot more mass.
否则星系会飞散
Other wise, the galaxy would have flown apart.
唯一解释这个星系快上10倍的悖论的途径
The only way to resolve this paradox...of galaxies which spin ten times too fast...
就是假设那里有一个光晕
is to assume that there is a halo...
一个无形物质组成的光晕围绕着星系
a halo of invisible matter surrounding the galaxy...
保持着星系的完整
keeping the galaxy whole.
暗物质存在于星系中
Dark matter was present in the galaxies...
它具有足够的质量来保持恒定的运转速度
and it had enough mass to keep the rotation speed constant.
把我想象成暗物质
lmagine that l am the dark matter.
这个球之围绕着我的恒星
This ball is a star orbiting me...
因为我的引力一直将它保持在空间
because my gravitational force is keeping it in place.
然而即使你看不到我
But even if you couldn't see me...
你也会知道这里必定有着什么东西
you would know there must be something here.
否则恒星就会沿着一条直线飞离
Otherwise, the star would just zoom off in a straight line.
必定存在着产生引力的某种东西
There must be something causing that gravity...
那就是我们知道必定存在着暗物质的原因所在
and that's how we know that there must be dark matter.
鲁宾估计暗物质比普通的发光体多出10倍
Rubin estimated that there was ten times more dark matter...han ordinary illuminated stuff.
此后 我们分析了数百个星系
Since then, we've analyzed hundreds of galaxies...
它们都是同样的情况
and they all have the same pattern.
它们都为了自身的利益旋转得非常快
They all rotate too fast for their own good...
它们都需要暗物质来抱成团
and they need dark matter to hold them together.
这一次科学界重视了
This time, science paid attention...
开始思索:暗物质是啥东西？
and started to wonder: What is dark matter?
你如何在太空中发现这无形的东西呢？
How do you find something that is invisible in space?
他们需要找到暗物质在宇宙间藏身之处
They needed to see just where dark matter...was hiding out in the universe.
即使他们无法看到
And even if they couldn't see it...
科学也已经认识到了暗物质通过弯曲经过的光
science realized that dark matter exposed itself...
自我暴露出来了
by bending light that passes through it.
这叫做引力透镜 实际上是个聚光灯
lt's called gravitational lensing, and it's a virtual spotlight...
暴露了宇宙间所有的无形物体
that uncovers any invisible stuff in the universe.
它的情况与所有的物质并无二异
What it does do is it does what all matter does...
因为它能够弯曲光线
in that it can deflect the light ray.
所以光线在传播过程中会被暗物质弯曲
So a light ray can be deflected in its path by dark matter.
通过追踪变形的光线
By tracing the battered light's path...
发现暗物质的引力透镜
gravitational lensing detected dark matter...
聚焦到了星系的光晕中
concentrated in the halos of galaxies.
引力透镜证明是极其准确的
Gravitational lensing proved to be infallible...
暗物质的存在突然被揭示了
and dark matter's presence was suddenly revealed.
这种引力透镜的技术
This technique of gravitational lensing...
是最准确的 因为我们实际上能够准确描述
is the most precise because we can actually pinpoint...
不仅是有多少暗物质存在
not just how much dark matter there is...
而且它分布在空间的具体位置
but how it's distributed in its position on the sky.
那是因为我们测量了光线经过暗物质的变形
And that's because we can measure the distortion...of the light rays passing through the dark matter.
你是怎么知道你的眼镜的位置的呢？
How do you know that your glasses are there?
因为它折射了光线
Because it bends light.
同样
ln the same way...
通过观察哈勃的宇宙空间照片
by looking at Hubble space pictures of the universe...
观察光线经过星系时的变形
and looking at the distortion of light...as it goes through galaxies...
我们就得到了暗物质的分布图
we actually have maps of dark matter.
星系的大部分质量来自暗物质
Most of the mass of a galaxy is from the dark matter.
普通的物质聚集在暗物质的引力场里
The ordinary matter accumulates...in the gravitational field of the dark matter.
然而一旦暗物质出现了
But once dark matter came on the scene...
科学家想知道 它究竟是一种新的未被侦检的粒子呢
scientists wondered if it was a new, undetected particle...
还只是无形的普通物质
orjust invisible ordinary matter.
在人们发现暗物质时
When people found dark matter...
大家都想知道 那是什么东东 知道吗
everybody wanted to know, well, what is it, you know?
当然啦最早的答案是
And, of course, the first answer is...
它只是构建你我的材料
it's just the stuff that makes up you and me...
只是不发光而已
but it's not shining.
科学家开始调查不发光的宇宙间的对象
Scientists started to investigate objects...in the universe that didn't emit light.
黑洞考虑到了
Black holes were considered.
它们不发光且能够将物质吸引过去
They don't emit light, can draw matter to themselves...
这已经通过引力透镜发现了
and are detected with gravitational lensing.
它的形式可能采用黑洞
lt could take a form of black holes...
或者MACHOs 大质量天体物理密实晕体
or MACHOs, massive compact halo objects...
那些基本上是昏暗的小恒星
which are basically dark, small stars...
不会发出太多的光
that don't give off a lot of light.
MACHOs隐藏在银河系的光晕外
MACHOs hide out in the halo of the Milky Way...
是通过引力透镜发现的
and are detected by gravitational lensing.
但够不上暗物质所需要的量
But there weren't enough...to account for the amount of dark matter needed.
褐矮星之类的衰败恒星也值得怀疑
Failed stars like brown dwarfs were also suspected.
它们数量可观足以弥补暗物质的存在
They are massive enough to make up dark matter's presence.
不管暗物质是什么 它超过
Whatever dark matter is, there is way more of it...
恒星和行星等普通物质10倍还多
than the ordinary matter of stars and planets...ten times more.
构成普通的原子 质子 中子 电子的所有材料
All the stuff that you can construct...from ordinary atoms, protons, and neutrons and electrons...
都不足以达到你所看到的星系和星团的物质总量
cannot possibly be enough...to account for the total amount of matter...that you see in galaxies and clusters.
科学家在继续搜寻暗物质的同时
Scientists continued to present new suspects...
不断提出新的嫌疑人
as the search continued for dark matter.
此前发现的奇异粒子
Previously discovered exotic particles...
比如中微子就被重新考虑了
like neutrinos, were reconsidered.
和暗物质一样中微子穿过地球
Like dark matter, neutrinos are passing through the Earth...
每秒钟数百万个粒子
millions of particles at a time...
但是它们太轻了
but they are too light...
难以解释暗物质对引力的影响
to account for dark matter's effect on gravity...
科学家可以在粒子对撞机里重现中微子
and scientists can recreate neutrinos in particle colliders.
他们同样来自太阳
They also come from the Sun.
轴子[Axions]是另一个潜在的暗物质粒子的候选者
Axions is also another possible dark matter candidate.
它们的发明是为了解释粒子物理理论中的一个特定的差错
They were invented to explain a particular glitch...in one of the particle physics theories.
它们会是非常轻
They would be extremely light...
所以你搜寻它们要以一个完全不同的方法
so you search for them in a completely different way...
相对我们在做的 但是会是…
than what we're doing, but there would be...
它们同样会是非常多的
They would also be very numerous.
因此它们有可能是暗物质
And so they could possibly be the dark matter.
轴子非常轻
Axions are very light...
被认为诞生于大爆炸那一刻就像暗物质一样
and are believed to have been created...at the moment of the Big Bang, just like dark matter.
但是理论上认为它们会变成质子
But theories suggest that they can change to protons...
然而暗物质是稳定的
while dark matter is stable.
在折腾了所有的一般嫌疑人后
After exhausting all the usual suspects...
许多科学家认为暗物质是一种新的奇异的粒子
many scientists believe dark matter is a new, exotic particle...
不同于地球上的任何东西
unlike anything on Earth...
每秒钟有数十亿个穿过我们
and billions are passing through us every second.
在发现暗物质之前
Up until the discovery of dark matter...
科学家一直认为宇宙的构成
scientists believed the universe...
只是质子 中子 电子
was made only of protons, neutrons, and electrons...
这些构成地球的材料
the stuff everything on Earth is made of.
我们知道还有一些物质
And we know it has some mass.
我们还有一些尚未被发现的东西
And we're left with something that we've not yet detected.
然而对于理想的暗物质候选者来说
But to be a perfect dark matter candidate...
它必须具有某些物理属性
it must have certain physical properties...
普通的嫌疑人都配不上这样的罪行
and none of the usual suspects were fitting the crime.
所以我们知道暗物质是某种笨重的物质
So we know the dark matter is some ponderous substance...
我们知道它运动得并不太快
we know that it's not moving too quickly...
我们知道我们无法看见它
and we know that we can't see it.
暗物质粒子并不以光速移动
Dark matter particles are not traveling at the speed of light...
它们并不会对你我或其它所有的东西产生影响
and they don't interact with you and me...
这就是为什么非常难以捕捉到这些粒子
or anything prettywell, and that's why it's been so difficult...to track down these particles.
它并不会对普通物质产生影响
And it doesn't interact with ordinary matter...
除了引力之外
except through gravity.
如果我手里有些暗物质
lf l had some dark matter in my hand...
它是具有分量的
it would have weight.
但是首先它会在我的指缝间消散掉
But first it would dissolve right through my fingers.
在我们所谓的标准模型粒子物理学里
There aren't any candidates for cold dark matter...
对于冷暗物质并没有任何嫌疑对象
within what we call the standard model particle physics.
和隐形人穿墙一样
Like an invisible man passing through walls...
每秒钟有数十亿个暗物质穿过地球
dark matter is passing through Earth billions of particles at a time...
从来没有碰撞到普通物质
never colliding with ordinary matter.
所以对于暗物质是什么的最普遍的概念
So the most popular idea for what the dark matter could be...
是叫做WIMP的东西
is something called a WlMP.
WIMP就是弱相互作用重粒子
WlMPs are weakly interacting massive particles.
它们从未被发现过 但是它们的特性
They have not been detected, but their characteristics...
匹配理想的暗物质嫌疑人
match the perfect dark matter candidate.
在苏丹实验室里
At the Soudan Laboratory...
费米实验室研究小组已经来到了地下
the Fermilab team has gone underground,,,
勇敢面对数以千计的蝙蝠
braving thousands of bats...
试图捕获到WIMP粒子
to try and capture a WlMP particle.
这就是所谓的低温暗物质搜寻
This is called the cryogenic dark matter search.
CDMS是其简称
CDMS is the acronym for it.
这里过去是个铁矿 直到1962年才被关闭
This was an iron ore mine until 1962 when it shut down.
我们在地下半英里处
We're half a mile underground.
费米实验室设计了一台机器 在零度以下的温度中
Fermilab has designed a machine that, at subzero temperatures...
可以检测经过其中的暗物质粒子
can detect a dark matter particle passing through it...
它的传感器用的材料是锗
and its sensor is made of germanium...
一种挤满原子的高密度金属
a dense metal jam-packed with atoms.
这是块高纯锗
lt's a very pure block of germanium.
在其表面
lt's got on the surface of it...
装有微小的温度计 基本上
a pattern of tiny little thermometers, basically...
能够发现粒子穿过这个曲棍球大小的锗块
that are able to detect when a particle passes...through this hockey puck-sized chunk of germanium.
暗物质现在正流过我们
Dark matter is streaming right through us right now...
没有任何动静
without doing anything.
极其偶然时它会撞上一个原子核
Very occasionally, it will bump into the nucleus of an atom.
那是我们希望看到的签名
And that's the signature that we're hoping to see.
为了得到一个清晰的暗物质撞击
To get a clean dark matter hit...
费米实验室需要过滤掉空间的垃圾
Fermilab needed to filter out junk from space.
我们会得到非常多的粒子
We would get so many particles...
这真的是在大海里捞针
that it would be really trying to sift a needle in a haystack.
费米实验室的实验收集
Fermilab's experiment picks up all matter...
所有经过这个探测器的物质
that passes through this detector.
空气中的垃圾越少
The lessjunk in the air...
发现暗物质粒子就越容易
the easier it will be to detect a dark matter particle.
因为暗物质不易对正常的质子和电子产生影响
Because dark matter doesn't interact easily...with regular protons and electrons...
费米实验室已经冷冻了锗块
Fermilab has frozen the germanium pucks...
温度接近了零下
to near subzero temperatures.
如果暗物质粒子穿过并击中了原子核
lf a dark matter particle comes through and hits a nucleus...
那么实际上会极细微地改变结晶体的温度
it will actually change the temperature of the crystal very slightly...
那么我们观察结晶体温度的细微变化
and so we're looking for that tiny change...of temperature in the crystal...
那是暗物质粒子经过的信号
to signal that a dark matter particle has passed by.
16个锗块安放在一个洁净室里
Sixteen germanium pucks...sit in a chamber inside a clean room.
我们穿好了工作服
So we're suited up...
将要进入实验室了
we're about to go into the experimental room.
这是个一万级的洁净室
lt's a Class 10,000 clean room.
那就是我们都要穿上工作服的原因 我们不能带进任何尘埃
That's whywe're all suited up so we don't carry in any dust...
因为会影响的实验的环境
because that would cause background for the experiment.
进去吧
So let's go inside.
这里有闪烁计数器
So we have scintillation counters...
正在捕捉任何到达这地下的宇宙射线的粒子
that are catching any cosmic-ray particles...that get all the way down underground here.
就是这 保持着我们实验的低温
So right here is what keeps our experiment cold...
比绝对零度稍高一点
a tiny little bit above absolute zero.
这是稀释制冷机
This is the dilution refrigerator.
这里面就是锗硅探测器
So way inside here...are the germanium and silicon detectors...
所以我们就等着WIMP暗物质粒子
so we're just waiting for a WlMP, a dark matter particle...
来到这深处
to get down to this depth...
撞击隐藏在保护罩里的这些锗硅结晶体中的一个
and hit one of those germanium and silicon crystals...that's buried way inside all the shields.
费米实验室在近两年里一直在光顾这座矿井
Fermilab has been visiting the mine for nearly two years...
试图捕捉到暗物质
trying to capture dark matter.
这谈何容易
This is far harder than it sounds.
尽管一次会有数十亿个粒子穿过地球
Although billions of particles are passing through Earth at one time...
但是百万分之一的概率
it's a one-in-a-million shot...
暗物质会和普通物质发生作用
dark matter will interact with ordinary matter.
让一个暗物质粒子撞击一个锗原子
Getting a dark matter particle to hit a germanium atom...
无异于弓箭手射中一英里开外的靶子的靶心
is like an archer trying to hit a bull's eye...when the target is a mile away.
所有这些绿灯指示出粒子在经过
All these green lights indicate particles...
我们在楼下看到的锗硅探测器
passing through the germanium and silicon detectors...that we saw downstairs.
这些几乎无疑是背景粒子
These are almost certainly all background particles.
然而或许隐藏在里面某个地方就是WIMP
But maybe it's buried in there someplace as a WlMP...
但是我们无从知晓 直到我们分析了数据
but we won't know until we analyze the data.
搜寻暗物质枯燥乏味
Hunting dark matter is tedious.
费米实验室研究小组每天会去地下实验室报到
Each day, the Fermilab team reports to the underground lab...
分析数据 提高乒乓球水平
analyzes data, and perfects their ping-pong game...
同时等着一次证明暗物质存在的撞击
while waiting for the one hit that will prove dark matter exists.
然而对于所有的努力和等待
But for all this effort and waiting around...
还没有暗物质被费米实验室以及其他人发现
no dark matter has been detected by Fermilab or by anyone else.
遗憾的是 迄今为止我们没有看到任何暗物质粒子
Unfortunately, we've seen...precisely zero dark matter particles so far.
现在任何时候我们都可能宣布
Any day now, we may have the announcement...
物理学家已经在瓶子里捕捉到了暗物质
that physicists have captured dark matter in a bottle.
我们有一个假设
We have a hypothesis.
似乎无疑能够解释我们所在的宇宙
lt certainly seems to explain the universe we live in.
但是明摆的事实就是我们尚未发现
But the plain fact is we haven't yet detected...
这种冷暗物质粒子
this cold dark matter particle.
找到暗物质将不仅给我们证明了它的存在
Finding dark matter will not only give us proof of its existence...
而且也回答了空间的其它大问题
but might also answer the other big questions of space.
发现暗物质将直接
Detecting dark matter directly...
为我们提供一个窗口 进入到
will give us a window onto what was going on...
大爆炸后的万分之一秒
1/10,000th of a second after the Big Bang.
如果科学家能够发现暗物质是什么
lf scientists can discover what dark matter is...
那么他们也就有可能发现宇宙子其早期的情况了
they might also discover how the universe behaved early in its life.
暗物质不仅是宇宙间的一个神秘的量
Dark matter is not only a mysterious quantity in the universe...
你要明白同时那也是必须要
but also it's fundamental to our, you know...
我们出现在这的原因
why we're here, in fact.
难以理解 形成星系
lt would be difficult to form galaxies...
从而 太阳系
and, hence, you know, the solar system...
从而 地球上的生命
and, hence, life on Earth.
暗物质和暗能量的故事
The story of dark matter and dark energy...
是说不清楚的 如果不回到时间的起点
can't be told without going back to the beginning of time...
不回到当时不存在空间的大爆炸的那个瞬间的话
to the moment of the Big Bang when space didn't exist.
不存在你能指出的中心位置
There was no center where you can point to.
这就是大爆炸的情况
And that's exactly the analogy for the Big Bang.
在空中漫无方向
There was no direction in the sky...
从那开始所有的星系都在不断地膨胀
from which all the galaxies were expanding.
从一无所有到剧烈地爆炸那一刻开始
From this moment of nothing to a violent explosion...
空间创造了 宇宙开始从一个种子成长起来
space was created, and the universe began to grow from a seed.
粒子形成于气体和能量的核聚变
Particles formed in a nuclearfusion of gas and energy.
普通物质与其它普通物质发生作用
Ordinary matter was reacting with other ordinary matter.
早期的宇宙在诞生后1分钟时
The early universe was in fact a nuclear reactor...
实际上是一座核反应堆
when it was one minute old.
38万年后粒子开始聚集起来
And 380,000 years later, bits of particles began to cluster...
形成了后来形成恒星以及星系的种子
creating the seeds from which stars and galaxies would laterform.
较大的团慢慢形成更大的团
Bigger lumps grow to form yet bigger lumps...
因此引力正缓慢地施加力量
and so gravity is a slowly pulling force...
将物体拉在一起
bringing objects together.
科学家现在认识到了在大爆炸的瞬间
What scientists now realize was that at the moment of the Big Bang...
暗物质也创造出来了
dark matter was created.
它在帮助普通物质结合起来形成恒星与行星中
And it played a critical role in helping ordinary matter...
发挥了关键的作用
clump together to form stars and planets.
就像钢梁用于建筑工地一样
Like steel girders used on a building site...
暗物质缓慢移动的粒子的作用就像是鹰架
dark matter's slow-moving particles acted like scaffolding...
普通物质就可以自己依附上去
upon which ordinary matter could attach itself.
我们认为那是因为它温度很低不会有太多的影响
We believe that, because it's cold and doesn't interact very much...
暗物质靠引力结合在一块
that dark matter was pulled together by gravity...
整个过程非常缓慢地形成种子
very slowly over time...and actually formed the seeds...
普通物质围绕着种子结合起来形成了星系
around which normal matter coalesced into galaxies.
这就像是宇宙网 就像是蜘蛛网
lt's like a cosmic web, like a spider's web...
那里存在着暗物质的丝线
where there are strands of dark matter...
这些丝线相互交叉 就像鹰架的模样
and where these strands intersect, like a scaffolding pattern.
所以在这里 暗物质就是构架
So in a sense, the dark matter is the framework.
它为我们能看到的闪亮的星系提供了构架
lt's providing the scaffolding...for the shining galaxies that we can easily see.
星系其实就像圣诞树上的灯泡
They are really like the Christmas tree lights.
而不是真正的圣诞树
They're not the actual Christmas tree.
它们是非常遥远都看得见的东西
They're the things that are visible from very, very far away.
然而真实的星系是一个大光晕
But the reality of the galaxy is a big halo...
其中的大部分你是看不见的
most of which you don't see.
你所看到的这些发光的点是恒星与行星
You see the shiny bits that are stars and planets...
都堆积在那个大光晕的中央
that have accumulated at the center of that large halo...
光晕的大部分是暗物质
which is mostly dark matter.
科学家长期以来困惑于为什么星系
Scientists have long wondered why galaxies formed...
会形成看似在空间中随意分布的格局
in seemingly random patterns across space.
现在科学家知道了那是因为暗物质的引力的作用
Now scientists know it's because of dark matter's gravitational pull.
宇宙根本不是均匀的而是有空隙的
The universe is not uniform at all, but has voids.
它有扎堆 有似乎有泡沫状的区域
lt has clumps, it seems to have bubble-like regions.
这个 我们现在认为那是由于暗物质的存在
Well, we now believe it's due to dark matter.
去年 天文学家已经能够将自己的理论更推进了一步
ln the last year, astronomers have been able...to take their theory one step further...
利用引力透镜
and create a detailed 3-D map...
创造出了一个详细的宇宙间暗物质的3D分布图
of dark matter in the universe, using gravitational lensing.
爱因斯坦称引力影响万物
And Einstein said that gravity affects everything...
就像引力是由万物引起的一样
just like gravity is caused by everything.
受引力影响的物体之一就是光本身
So one of the things that is affected by gravity is light itself.
因为光经过暗物质 会弯曲
Because when light goes through dark matter, it bends...
就像光经过眼镜时受到弯曲那样
just the way light bends when it goes through glass.
光不会区别对待普通物质和暗物质
And light doesn't discriminate between ordinary matter and dark.
两种物质在光穿越星系时 都会改变它的路径
Both types of matter batter light's path as it travels through galaxies.
就像在地图上绘制航线一样
Like plotting a course on a map...
天文学家追踪了数以千计的穿越暗物质的光源
astronomers have traced thousands of light sources...as they pass through dark matter.
这给了科学最精准的图像
lt has given science the most accurate picture yet...
指出了暗物质在空间里的藏身之处
of where dark matter hides in space.
我们可以比较暗物质与星系的分布图
We can compare that map of the dark matter...
你瞧
with where the galaxies are, and, lo and behold...
我们发现暗物质正充当着骨架
we find that the dark matter is acting as the skeleton.
就是围绕着这骨架 有形的物质聚集起来
lt is the backbone around which the visible material is clumping.
通过绘制宇宙的地图天文学家也能够回头去看
By mapping the universe, astronomers can also look back in time...
预测在大爆炸时究竟创造出了多少物质
and predict how much matter was created at the Big Bang.
如果你知道了宇宙现在显示出来的块头
So ifyou know how lumpy the universe appears now...
当年它在现在一半大的时候的块头
and when it was half its current size...
还有更早时的块头
and when it was half its current size before that...
那么你就可以推断出宇宙中的物质总量了
you can infer the total amount of stuff in the universe.
这就给了我们一个非常好的匹配方法
lt gives us another very nice way of matching on...
我们认为那就是暗物质的总量
to what we believe is the total amount of dark matter.
我们估计暗物质
lt's estimated dark matter...
占到宇宙的23%
makes up twenty-three percent of the universe...
而普通物质只占4%
while ordinary matter makes up only four percent.
你需要大量的暗物质
You need a lot of dark matter...
来解释这些星团和星系中所存在的引力的总量
to account for the total amount of gravity...that exists in these clusters and galaxies.
然而 占到宇宙最后73%的究竟是什么呢？
But what makes up the final seventy-three percent of the universe?
科学家惊讶地发现
Scientists were shocked to discover...
一种神秘的暗能量正主宰着空间
a new mysterious dark energy was dominating space.
其排斥能正将星系拉开
And its repulsive energy is driving the galaxies apart.
科学一贯假设
Science always assumed...
尽管宇宙在不断地增大
that although the universe continues to grow in size...
但是它终究会放慢膨胀
it would eventually slow in its expansion...
甚至有可能自我塌缩
or perhaps even collapse on itself.
引力会战胜它具有的所有的动能
Gravity would overcome any momentum it had.
但是在测量宇宙的膨胀史时
But while measuring the expansion history of the universe...
科学家惊讶地意识到
scientists were shocked to realize...
宇宙并未慢下来
that the universe wasn't slowing down.
它还在加速
lt was speeding up...
严酷的命运等待着所有的生命
and a grim fate awaited any living thing.
宇宙会分裂
The universe will disintegrate...
温度会变得非常的低
and temperatures will become so cold...
任何智能生命都将冻死
that any intelligent life will freeze to death.
从大爆炸创造出了宇宙的那一刻开始
From the moment the Big Bang created the universe...
空间就一直在膨胀 从未停下脚步
space has been expanding and never stopping...
带着星系一路前进
carrying galaxies along for the ride.
星系间的空间正在膨胀
The space in between the galaxies is expanding.
星系却没有膨胀
The galaxies are not expanding.
地球没有膨胀
The Earth is not expanding.
太阳系没有膨胀
The solar system is not expanding.
哈勃在1929年第一个发现了
Edwin Hubble first discovered...
星系在远离银河系
galaxies were moving away from the Milky Way in 1929...
基于了解到较为遥远的星系
by realizing the more distant galaxies...
远离我们的速度比较近的星系来得快
move faster away from us than the nearby ones.
他意识到自己可以通过研究它们经过菱镜的波长
He realized he could measure theirvelocities...
来测量它们的速度
by studying their wavelengths through a prism.
它就是所谓的测量红移
lt's called measuring the red shift...
它还被用于测量空间的距离
and is still used to measure distances in space.
他发现事实上
And he found that, in fact...
星系的距离越远
the greater the distance of a galaxy right now...
它们离开我们的速度就越大
the greater the speed with which it's moving away from us.
换句话就是红移越大
That is, the greater its red shift.
几年前
A few years ago...
天文学家决定用红移测量
astronomers decided to use red shift measurements...
来测定宇宙的膨胀史
to measure the expansion history of the universe.
但是你如何去测量
But how do you measure...
宇宙的整个膨胀史呢？
the entire expansion history of the universe?
你如何回到120亿年前呢？
How do you travel back twelve billion years in time?
我们具有追溯时间的能力
We have the capability of going back in time directly...
直接观察过去
to observe the past.
这个 和地质学家同样的手段 要知道
So, much in the same way as a geologist, you know...
观察大峡谷的岩层
looks at layers in the Grand Canyon...
随着他记录下往下一层又一层的岩层
and as he goes down into lower and lower layers...
就看到了历史的过去
looking back in history.
如果你看到更为遥远的星系
lfyou look at progressively more distant galaxies...
你就看到了它们在更早时期的模样了
you're looking at them as theywere...at progressively greater times in the past.
为了测量膨胀的历史 科学家利用1A类超新星
To measure expansion history, scientists used Type 1a supernovas...
作为他们的标准烛光
as their standard candle.
举个例子 标准烛光可能就是一个100瓦的灯泡
One example of a standard candle might be a100-watt light bulb.
你可以将灯泡这样的东西
You could have a bunch of these things...
安放在房间四处与你不同距离的地方
sitting around in your room at different distances from you.
于是较远的就会显得较昏暗
Then the more distant ones will appear fainter...
较近的就会显得较亮
and the more nearby ones will appear brighter.
1A类超新星始终恒定地发光
Type1a supernovas are always consistently brilliant...
无论它们身处太空的何处
no matter where they occur in space.
超新星恒星在其生命终结时急剧的膨胀
A supernova is the colossal explosion of a star...at the end of its life.
就是一声巨响!
lt just goes kabam.
当它成为一颗垂死的恒星时 所谓的白矮星
And it occurs when a dying star, known as a white dwarf...
经历了核心的爆发
goes through a nuclear runaway...
把其自身喷发成碎片
and just literally blows itself to smithereens.
我们发现1A类超新星在非常遥远的星系里
We find the Type 1a supernovae in very distant galaxies...
所以看上去很昏暗
so they look really faint.
于是我们将它们与较近的星系里的1A类超新星
And then we compare them with Type1a supernovae...
相比较它们的距离
in nearby galaxies whose distance were...
距离的测量是利用造父变星
Distances were measured using Cepheid variables...
或其它一些技巧
or some other technique.
利用这些1A类超新星
Using these Type 1a supernovas...
1990年代分别有两个研究小组
two different teams set out in the 1990s...
来测量宇宙的减速速度
to measure the deceleration rate of the universe.
然而为了在超新星出现是捕捉到它们
But to capture supernovas as they occur...
天文学家必须紧盯宇宙不放
astronomers had to put the universe on surveillance.
你可以将这个比作赌场监视
You can compare this a little bit to perhaps surveying a casino.
所有的探头全程打开
So all these cameras are on all the time...
大部分时间里它们不会发现很多的有趣事情的
and most of the time, they don't find much of anything interesting.
但是偶 它们会发现要观察的东西的
But, occasionally, they find what they're looking for.
你必须要观察大量的星系
You have to look at lots of galaxies.
所以我们做的就是用上大望远镜
So what we did is we took large telescopes...
装上广角相机
with cameras that have wide fields ofview...
所谓的广角就是满月的宽度
about as wide as, say, the width of the full Moon.
我们会利用这个广角相机拍上许多太空的快照
And we took many snapshots of space using this wide-field camera.
每张快照包括了数万个星系
And each snapshot contains tens of thousands of galaxies.
通过将遥远的1A类超新星的亮度
And by comparing the apparent brightness of the distant Type 1a's...
对比较近的星系里的1A类超新星的亮度
with those of the nearby Type 1a's in nearby galaxies...
我们就能够得出遥远星系的距离
we can get the distance of the distant galaxies...
随着时间的积累
and, hence, the amount of time...
我们就回顾了宇宙的历史
that we're looking back in the history of the universe.
在两个小组得到了60个1A类超新星的研究结果后
After the two teams studied the results...of sixty Type 1a supernovas...
科学家被他们的结果震惊了
scientists were shocked at their results.
宇宙并没有放慢脚步
The universe wasn't slowing down.
其膨胀还在加速
lts expansion was speeding up.
我们都预计膨胀随着时间的推移在减缓
We all expected that expansion to be slowing down with time...
因为 毕竟所有的星系在相互吸引
because, after all, all of the galaxies are pulling on one another.
我们非常肯定我们将测量到宇宙放慢的速度
We were so confident we were going to measure the rate...at which the universe was slowing down...
当然我们发现的却是相反的答案
and then we found, of course, a negative answer.
宇宙并没有放慢脚步
The universe is not slowing down.
它在加速
lt's speeding up...
这真是个大谜团
and this was just a big mystery.
这真的是非常怪异
That is really, really weird.
你知道 我们曾预计测量到一定程度的减缓
You know, we expected to measure some amount of slowdown...
相反 它的膨胀越发加快了
and instead, it's expanding more quickly.
那就像是个错误的信号对吧？
That's like the wrong sign, right?
我们真的很担心
We were really afraid...
我们得到的是完全错误的答案
that we had gotten completely the wrong answer.
我们再次检查了我们的测量成果
We rechecked our measurements.
我们检查了分析报告
We checked the analysis.
两个小组各自都有一帮人
A bunch of people on each of the two teams...
进行测量 独立分析
did the measurements and the analysis independently...
不断得出同样的结果
and kept getting the same result.
宇宙学界最近几年里最大的冲击之一
One of the greatest shocks in the world of cosmology...
已经认识到了我们的宇宙在加速
just in the last few years has been the realization...that our universe is accelerating.
这个驱动宇宙的排斥力
This repulsive force driving the universe...
叫做暗能量 一种无形的能量
was called dark energy, an invisible energy...
谁都没有料到的 无法理解的东西
that was nothing anyone expected or understood.
它表明在宇宙的最大距离范围内
lt suggests that over the largest distances in the universe...
存在着一种排斥力 超过了引力
there's a repulsive effect that dominates over gravity.
暗能量在创造空间
And dark energy was creating space...
拉着星系一路往前
taking galaxies along for the ride.
这种始终充满了宇宙
This energy that appears to fill the universe...
延展宇宙膨胀越来越快的能量
and stretch the expansion of the universe...
就是现在所谓的暗能量
faster and faster with time is now known as dark energy.
这里我要扔出一个苹果 它开始减速了
So here l throw the apple, and, initially, it's decelerating.
然而暗能量会把它加速远离我
And then dark energy makes it accelerate away from me.
所以你扔出苹果
So you throw the apple...
它就会飞离 一路加快
and it just zooms away faster and faster with time.
和苹果一路飞进太空一样
Like the apple forever traveling into space...
星系被一路带到了创造出来的更大的空间里
galaxies are being carried away as more space is created.
如果你能想象一下的话
So ifyou could imagine, you know...
教室里摆着椅子
a classroom populated by chairs...
那些椅子在教室里正慢慢地相互分开
and those chairs are slowly getting further apart...from one another within a classroom...
因为 要是所有的椅子像膨胀的宇宙一样延展开
because if all the chairs are being stretched apart...like in the expanding universe...
不论你坐在那把椅子上
no matter which chair you sit on...
你都会发现所有的椅子都在远离你
you will find all chairs are moving away from you.
所以椅子并没有真的膨胀
So the chairs are not really expanding.
事实上 椅子的大小确实没有变化
ln fact, the chairs are all the same size, really.
结果是房间变得越来越大了
What's happening is that the room is getting bigger...
椅子之间的空间变得越来越开了
the sort of the space in between the chairs...is being stretched apart.
星系间正在创造出更大的空间
More space is being created in between the galaxies.
所以 你看到单个的星系在宇宙中保持着固定的大小
So you have individual galaxies remaining a constant size...
整个空间变得越来越大了
in a universe where all of space is getting bigger and bigger.
暗能量完全不同于暗物质
Dark energy is very different from dark matter.
它不会像星团里的星系
lt doesn't clump up like galaxies do in clusters...
或星系里的恒星那样抱团
or like stars do in galaxies.
相反它表现出相当的均匀
lnstead, it appears to be pretty uniform.
我们发现等量的加速度
And we find the same amount of acceleration...
无论我们往哪个方向看
no matter which direction we look at.
它或许很平滑
lt's probably smooth...
尽管 有些人认为在其分布和影响中有可能存在纹理
although some people believe there may be structure...in its distribution and its influence.
暗能量是虚无的能量
Dark energy is the energy of the vacuum...
看不见 摸不着
the energy of nothing.
虚无缥缈之中具有能量
Even nothingness has energy.
它将星系推开 创造失控的宇宙
And it's pushing the galaxies apart, creating a runaway universe.
看来暗能量和暗物质
lt appears dark energy and dark matter...
自时间开创以来就一直在相互竞争
have been at war with one another since the beginning of time.
科学家认为在大爆炸的那一刻
Science believes dark energy was created...
暗能量与暗物质一道诞生了
along with dark matter at the moment of the Big Bang.
它一直存在于宇宙间
lt has always existed in the universe...
但是暗物质的引力保持着对它的控制
but gravitational forces of dark matter kept it in check...
在最早的90亿年里
slowing down the expansion of space...
减缓了空间的膨胀
during the first nine billion years of time.
这在50亿年前变化了
This changed five billion years ago...
当时宇宙已经成长得够大了
when the universe grew big enough...
所以暗物质分布遍及整个宇宙
so that dark matter was dispersed throughout the universe...
暗能量已经不再受到暗物质引力的影响了
and dark energy wasn't so affected by dark matter's pull.
结果宇宙开始加速膨胀
As a result, the universe began to expand...at an accelerated rate.
暗能量在宇宙最初的高温高密度的情况下
Dark energy is a constant term that was probably very insignificant...
或许是个微不足道的常数项
when the universe was hot and dense in the beginning...
所以真的无关紧要
and so it doesn't really matter...
不管暗能量是否存在
whether dark energy is there or not.
它存在 但根本就没有什么作用
lt is there, but it's... lt just plays no role at all.
然后随着宇宙变得越来越冷 密度越来越小 个头越来越大
And then, as the universe gets cooler and less dense and bigger...
所以引力变得越来越重要
so gravity becomes less important...
于是暗能量有戏唱了
and then dark energy takes over.
这个空间特性我们尚未完全搞明白
lt's a property of space that we don't yet fully understand.
随着宇宙的膨胀天文学家意识到暗能量
As the universe expanded, astronomers realized dark energy...
赢得了与暗物质的斗争
won its struggle with dark matter...
在50亿年前开始了加速
and started the acceleration five billion years ago.
所以有一段时间 约50亿年前
So there came a time, about five billion years ago...
暗能量开始主宰宇宙间的有吸引力的物质
when the dark energy started dominating...over the attractive matter in the universe.
所以 在这里 如果你绘出力与时间矢量表
So, in a sense, ifyou plot force versus time...
万有引力一路下滑
the gravitational attraction is declining with time...
排斥力则一路攀升
the repulsion is increasing with time...
约在50亿年前 两个曲线交汇了
and about five billion years ago, the two curves crossed...
就在那时 宇宙开始加速膨胀了
and that's when the universe started accelerating in its expansion.
暗能量是需要搞明白的关键
Dark energy is fundamental to understand...
因为 它会告诉我们宇宙的未来
because it tells us where the universe is going.
宇宙的结局是什么？
What's the fate of the universe?
它是永远膨胀变得又冷又黑吗？
ls it going to expand forever and get cold and dark?
还是有那么一点尽头？
Or is there, you know, some end in sight?
暗能量现在驱动着宇宙的膨胀
Dark energy now drives the expansion of the universe...
看似不会停下来
and it doesn't seem to be stopping.
暗能量的排斥力增强了
The repulsive effect of the dark energy increased...
因为星系间的空间越大
because the more space there is between galaxies...
暗能量积累的力量 排斥力就越强
the greater is the cumulative effect...of the dark energy, the repulsive effect.
每个星系命中注定将孤单地生存
And individual galaxies seem destined to a lonely existence.
因此 这看上去就像是万物的结局
So it looks as ifthis is the end of everything.
令人惊讶的是 暗能量理论
Surprisingly, the theory of dark energy...
在很早以前就被物理学上
was proposed and discarded long ago...
一个最伟大的人物提出和抛弃过
from one of physics' greatest minds.
他称它是自己最大的失误
He called it his biggest blunder.
他的名字叫爱因斯坦 他可能已经
His name was Einstein, and he might have been...
扎进这个21世纪最伟大的发现
onto the greatest discovery of the 21st century...
比别人提出早了8年
eighty years before anyone had a clue.
科学界现在明白了
Science now understands...
暗能量正在创造和扩展空间
that dark energy is creating and expanding space.
但是早在20世纪初
But in the early 20th century...
天文学家认为宇宙只有银河系那么大
astronomers believed the universe was only as big...
空间永远不会扩展
as the Milky Way and would never grow in size.
然而 爱因斯坦就已经形成了自己的相对论
But Einstein had just formed his theory of relativity...
并决定在静态宇宙里来测试它
and decided to test it on the static universe.
但是爱因斯坦的尝试困难重重
But as hard as Einstein tried...
他平衡不了自己的静态宇宙的方程式
he could not balance his equation to equal a static universe.
他的计算显示出宇宙
His calculations showed a universe...
必须要么是膨胀的要么是收缩的
that must either expand or contract.
他意识到如果你看到的宇宙是平滑的
He realized that ifyou had a universe that was smooth...
物质均匀分布的
that was uniformly distributed with stuff...
那么他的理论明确预示了
his theory unambiguously predicted...
它应该不是膨胀的就是收缩的
that it should either be expanding or contracting.
因此 爱因斯坦提出了一个令人讨厌的真空能
So Einstein proposed a repulsive vacuum energy...
来保证宇宙在引力上的平衡
that would hold the universe in balance with attractive gravity.
他称它为自己的宇宙常数
He called it his cosmological constant...
一个保持宇宙平衡的恒定的能量
a constant energy that would hold the universe in balance.
他提出了宇宙常数
He introduced the cosmological constant...
即暗能量来保持宇宙的稳定
or dark energy, to hold the universe static.
当时哈勃提出了空间在膨胀
When Hubble announced space was expanding...
突然间 爱因斯坦的宇宙常数似乎无关了
suddenly, Einstein's cosmological constant seemed irrelevant...
他把它列为自己最大的失误
and he labeled it his biggest blunder.
现在结果是 暗能量
Now it turns out that dark energy...
一个他早在1920年代就抛弃了的概念 事实上
a concept that he threw away back in the 1920s, is, in fact...
成了将宇宙拆散的主导力量了
the dominant force blowing the universe apart.
爱因斯坦的所谓失误
Einstein's so-called blunder...
将最终决定宇宙究竟是葬身于冰还是火
will eventually determine whether or not...the universe dies in fire or ice.
打赌是宇宙将葬身于冰
And the betting is the universe will die in ice.
在努力纵览宇宙的举止中
ln trying to survey how the universe behaves...
爱因斯坦错误地预测了暗能量
Einstein had erroneously predicted dark energy...
就是宇宙总的成分
and what is the total makeup of the universe.
普通物质和暗物质里的物质总量
The total amount of stuff in the ordinary matter and dark matter...
还不足以解释我们所观察到的空间的弯曲
is not enough to account for the curvature of space...that we observe.
如同观察地球的地平线一样
Like looking across a horizon on Earth...
宇宙的规模如此之大
the size of the universe is so great...
空间的弯曲表现的很平坦
the curvature of space appears flat.
普通物质 暗物质 暗能量加在一起
Add ordinary matter, dark matter, and dark energy together...
才能做出空间弯曲的预测
that makes a prediction for the curvature of space.
那个预测已有端倪
And that prediction comes spot on.
你会得到正确的答案的
You get the right answer.
我们的卫星数据现在已经揭示了这样的事实
Our satellite data now has revealed the fact...
宇宙间物质能量的73%是暗能量
that seventy-three percent of the matter-energy content...of the universe is dark energy.
暗能量这个曾经的爱因斯坦的失误
Dark energy, which was once Einstein's blunder...
现在已广为人知是宇宙的支配力了
is now known to be the dominant force in the universe.
他的失误是我们伟大的发现
His blunders are our great discoveries.
科学家刚刚起步了解
Scientists are at the very beginning of understanding...
暗能量将会对宇宙的命运有什么影响
what effect dark energy will have on the fate of the universe.
理想情况下我们欲测量
ldeally, we'd like to measure...
暗能量在宇宙的成长中是如何表现的
how dark energy is behaving as the universe ages.
最终一旦暗能量完全战胜了暗物质
Eventually, when the dark energy...completely dominates over dark matter...
宇宙将进入指数膨胀的阶段
the universe will enter a stage known as exponential expansion.
对于给一个特定的时间段来说 都将扩大一倍…
For every given unit of time, it'll double in size...
除非暗能量有朝一日有改变的迹象
And unless the dark energy changes sign someday...
变成了万有引力
and becomes gravitationally attractive...
否则宇宙的命运将是膨胀永无止境
the fate of the universe is to expand forever...
一直越来越快
more and more quickly with time.
我们不明白 如果真空能正驱动着宇宙的加速度
We don't understand if the vacuum energy is driving...
那么为何它会具有那样的量的呢？
the acceleration of the universe, why it has the amount it does.
那是今天理论物理学有待解决的最大的难题之一
That is one of the deepest puzzles...remaining in theoretical physics today.
往后万亿年后
Trillions of years from now...
这里将是一片荒凉的空间
it's going to be a very lonely place.
我们仰视天空
We'll look up in the sky...
天空将暗无天日
and the skies will be practically dark.
大海顿失滔滔
The oceans will freeze over...
看来仿佛这就是所有智能生命的归宿
and it looks as ifthis is the death of all intelligent life.
看来仿佛暗能量以及物理定律
lt looks as if dark energy and the laws of physics...
都宣判了宇宙间所有智能生命的死刑
are a death warrant to all intelligent life in the universe.
在发现暗能量和暗物质的过程中
ln discovering dark matter and dark energy...
科学界向万有理论靠近了一步
science is one step closer to defining the theory of everything:
一个能界定宇宙整个运作的方程式
One equation that will define the entire workings of the universe.
过去我们有过万有理论
Once we have the theory of everything...
我们将能够回答自男人和女人注视天堂以来
we'll be able to answer some of the deepest questions...
的某些最深层的问题
ever since man and women first looked at the heavens.
这可能是希腊人提出 "万物是什么构成的？"的问题
This could be the crowning achievement...of 2,000 years of investigation into the laws of nature...
2000年以来探索自然法则的最大成就
ever since the Greeks asked the question..."What are things made of?"
目前 暗物质和暗能量
For now, dark matter and dark energy...
是21世纪有待解决的最大的宇宙问题
continue to be the greatest cosmological questions...of the 21st century.
这当然令人沮丧
lt's certainly frustrating.
我的意思是令人感到难为情 去了解
Yes, l mean, it's humbling, too, to know that...
知道吗 我们所有的物理知识
you know, all that we know about physics...
局限于普通物质
is restricted to normal matter...
可是所有这些暗物质 暗能量
and yet there's all this other dark matter and dark energy...
我们真的了解甚少
that we really understand very little about.
这就是揭开宇宙黑暗一面的新纪元的开始
lt's the beginning of a new era and the mysteries...of the dark side of the universe.
这里是粒子天体物理学方面的大西部
lt's the Wild West as far as particle astrophysics...
这就是我们对这个领域的称谓
which is what we call this field.
这就是我们尚未完全了解的空间特性
lt's a property of space that we don't yet fully understand.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing